<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jaidevshriram.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jaidevshriram.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-13T06:05:56+00:00</updated><id>https://jaidevshriram.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Noise in Applied vs Academic Research</title><link href="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/noise-in-applied-vs-academic-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Noise in Applied vs Academic Research"/><published>2023-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/noise-in-applied-vs-academic-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/noise-in-applied-vs-academic-research/"><![CDATA[<p>Computer vision research is tough and more annoyingly, quite competitive. The field moves extremely quickly and many ideas are simultaneously being worked on by amazing groups worldwide. Recently, I wondered if I could satisfy my research inclinations by working on its more applied side, one that was industry facing and more result oriented, rather than academia. It was a lot of fun but I discovered that it was in fact just as tough albeit in a very different way.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>When I first started out doing robotics research, I often felt very overwhelmed by the number of papers coming out in machine learning, each of which promised to be the new state of the art. Every once in a while, papers would also claim to change the way we train models altogether, which severely confused this new student in ML. For instance, I remember reading a paper on <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.02177">Grokking</a>, the phenomenon where a model achieves generalization long after it had overfit to a dataset. Now, while I tried to improve the generalization of my model, I wondered, if my training paradigm was what was wrong, not the model. Looking back I see it differently.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>Academic research in my view is producing novel insights with the luxury or even the penalty of certain assumptions. Applied research is the translation of these ideas into practice while removing as many assumptions as economically possible.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>In the context of grokking, my research question was less about how we can obtain the best metric on a leaderboard, but rather, how we can learn something new about the task at hand using many of the same assumptions as prior work - including their training paradigm. Academic research is very focused and very precise, to the point that it’s okay if you ignore developments like grokking for a project. One of my advisors at that time pointed out that if it doesn’t singularly furthen that one research question, it’s maybe not that relevant. Further, if you’re approach is changing too often as a result of new papers, maybe the original question itself is too noisy.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>On the other hand, applied research is a lot less focused. For instance, in robotics, a lot of research assumes you have a monocular camera and tries to push 3D perception using just that. In practice, self-driving cars and trucks have multiple cameras, LiDARs, and other redundant sensors. In this case, the assumptions made in academia make the problem tougher than it is in real life. So, when we move to the industry, the toolkit to work with is a lot wider, the available techniques more, and the possibility for poor results higher as well since it’s out in the real world. As a result, the type of creative thinking you do is very different too.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>I interned at a self driving truck startup this summer - <a href="https://plus.ai/">Plus AI</a> - and this was one of the surprising things I learnt. If a lot of academic research noise is determining what to work on, applied research noise is determining what ideas potentially matter. In academia, it’s okay to work with select datasets but in the industry that’s not enough. Hence, during the internship I found it quite confusing to have a clear idea on how best to frame a problem. At one point I was thinking about 3D object reconstruction on highways and just felt confused at the wide variety of solutions that I could’ve used (Optimization based, feed-forward, 2D priors, 3D priors, etc). The question was no longer, what’s novel enough for a conference, but what was good enough to work for many months/years. To be honest, even after the internship I’m not completely sure! All I know is that the best skill to have regardless of what you’re doing is understanding concepts at various levels of abstraction while being opinionated about them.</p> <p><br/></p>]]></content><author><name>Jaidev Shriram</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I thought applied research would be easier than academic but it’s not]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tooling is important. Who knew?</title><link href="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/tooling-is-important-who-knew/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tooling is important. Who knew?"/><published>2023-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/tooling-is-important-who-knew</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/tooling-is-important-who-knew/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently worked in a team for a class project and I think the most educational thing I took from that course was how my teammate worked. I’ve known a lot of people who are good at CS, but it’s the people who I considered to be great that slightly eluded me. What was the thing that made them slightly more effective, slightly more in command of their material, and slightly more comfortable in the field. Until said class project, I think I missed one huge aspect of it - the tools that they used, or more often, built for themselves to aid their productivity.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>For instance, we were tasked with building a mildly complex VR controller interaction system in Unity. The catch was that we could only use the controller while in the lab. And if you aren’t familiar with Unity, know that it is quite slow and annoying to iterate with. As such, building a working controller interaction meant sitting in the CS basement for hours with no snacks nearby (the horror). What my teammate did that surprised me, was that he built a bare bones emulator for that controller in Unity, to simulate how it might behave. Motions of the controller were aliased to keys on the keyboard and a simple cube visually represented the controller in the game scene. The result? A sufficient emulation of the controller that let us work at home, avoid the controller API, and test the essential parts of the system. It probably took a short while to build this, but it saved us many hours.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>I’ve increasingly realized that good tools can be an essential part of the development process. What may seem like a time sink in a tangential direction is simply an investment in a more comfortable journey ahead. And these tools can be temporary, serving just for the use case at hand but they can still make an impact. What’s key here is to be cognizant about our personal frictions - the hidden forces that make tasks more difficult or unappealing to us. Anything that we can do to remove the slightest friction is time well spent - friction is hard to notice but the second you are without it, you’ll realise the difference.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>Once a teammate of mine set up email alerts to monitor our experiments that ran on a server, a seemingly small thing but one that stopped us from babysitting our experiments, letting us move on in life. Now, I find myself wishing that I had a similar system for my experiments at UCSD since I often stare at my kubernetes pods just to ensure that they don’t die randomly.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>I should probably build that.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>PS: This blog is in some ways my personal evidence for building better tools for my workflows. I recently integrated notion with my jekyll theme and set up Github actions for automatic deployment of the website. By decoupling writing from the web-dev process, there’s virtually no friction in blogging anymore.</p> <p><br/></p>]]></content><author><name>Jaidev Shriram</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Productivity can improve with better tools, so build them]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Calibrating Dreams or Flying a Plane</title><link href="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/calibrating-dreams-or-flying-a-plane/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calibrating Dreams or Flying a Plane"/><published>2023-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/calibrating-dreams-or-flying-a-plane</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2023/calibrating-dreams-or-flying-a-plane/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/3122d440-75c1-4155-88d2-061d78141720/ee05d853-d6d4-4146-8761-87d0758e1969/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=AKIAT73L2G45FSPPWI6X%2F20241213%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20241213T060602Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Signature=a1f2e457a053f3929c944c3f8d79d24427a631b7706c834db2f547d4de8223d7&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt=""/></p> <p>Dreams are so much fun.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>I’d say that I am a chronic daydreamer, constantly thinking about what could be, getting excited by the prospect of anything new, making me an optimist in an often naive sense. My daydreaming extends to things from my everyday life, and in the context of this text, things that I pursue in university or even independently.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>By daydreaming, I refer to the sort of mental escapism where you imagine the future, what you are doing then, and simply try to hallucinate what’s at the end of the tunnel, to the point that the act of hallucination gives you some joy. I don’t think that’s bad - you need this type of thinking to stay excited about anything in life! However, daydreaming can set us for disappointment by placing us in a future that doesn’t yet exist. Couple that with anxiety about hitting your personal goals, you have a pretty good recipe for disappointing yourself. It’s easy to have grand dreams, fun to be optimistic about achieving them, and sadly, gut-wrenching when they don’t come true. This is something I find myself doing quite often in life.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>The way I approach a new topic these days usually looks something like this:</p> <ul> <li>Panic about entering something unknown</li> <li>Learn the teeniest thing about the topic and get super excited</li> <li>Start thinking about how ideas in that tiny concept might be related to other projects I am involved in, such as my research</li> <li>Have grand ideas about doing something novel/interdisciplinary in this field</li> <li>Get anxious about my inability to truly do so</li> <li>Feel defeated when that anxiety is proven right</li> </ul> <p><br/></p> <p>This way of thinking is arguably encouraged by the course structure in universities - where final projects are often expected to be novel and mini forays into research. The sort of ambition this coursework expects is uncalibrated - it is simply unrealistic to do something that is groundbreaking within a span of three months, at a pace of 3 hours a week. Even beyond coursework, I see this in a lot of educational content that’s marketed online - proficiency at the highest level is made to seem achievable in a short span of time. When you buy into that ideology and fail to meet the expectation, the lesson you take away is that you are not good enough. I think the more accurate and healthier lesson to take away is that the learning environment was not conducive to actual learning. More broadly, I think this ties into a phenomenon in computer science that I’d call ‘Tutorialitis’.</p> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="tutorialitis">Tutorialitis</h2> <p><br/></p> <p>I’d define ‘Tutorialitis’ as the *condition that appears when one is so accustomed to consuming quick-tutorial based content, that they feel dizzy when taken into another slower learning environment. *‘Tutorialitis’ is based on the proliferation of concepts and ideas in a field through bite-sized tutorials that are meant to get quick results, often at the cost of an in-depth understanding of the subject material.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>When I was first starting out in CS, I was drawn to web development - like most people are. It was easy to set up, fun to visualise, and quick to iterate with. I spent quite a bit of time in the first year of undergrad tinkering with frontend frameworks and prototyping websites. Back then, I believed that this interest was due to the creative nature of the work, which I think is accurate but an incomplete picture. It was also the easiest thing to pick up. I’d attribute this ease to the murky concept of ‘intuitiveness’. With just a few minutes in an editor, you can get a sense of how HTML might work. Combine the quick pace of tutorials with a quick learning curve, which help you get pretty results very soon, you feel accomplished quite easily. An unintentional lesson I took away from that experience was that this is how you are supposed to pick up topics. Anything that strayed from this pattern was perceived as something that I’m <strong>intrinsically</strong> bad at.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>In this case, ‘Tutorialitis’ leads to one misattributing their difficulties in a certain domain to their ability, when it is more likely something to do with how they are approaching the problem. I find that I take a very aggressive approach when learning a new topic/skill. I can very easily get excited, open several browser tabs, and start exploring something new. The momentum never sticks though. In some ways, this can be seen as my attempt at recreating the quick pace of tutorials that I’ve previously done. I’m so invested in the idea of moving forward that I just try to run forward and inevitably stumble.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>A nice analogy for this situation that’s helped me in recent weeks is that of a plane that’s trying to take off. Planes have a long runway for a reason - they need time to reach the high velocity that’s required for takeoff. That’s just part one though. Once they do lift off, the angle at which it pitches up also matters; you want it to be high so that you gain altitude quickly but not so high that you lose thrust and stall completely. The way I’ve been trying to pick-up new topics is to pitch up so high that I immediately stall and crash the plane, never truly picking up the topic I intended to.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>All this ties back to the concept of daydreaming. You only pitch the plane up when you are dead set on going higher, in pursuit of some dream that you have. When you focus so intently on the final goal, you can stall and forget about how the learning process is supposed to go. The healthier way to do it is to accept that you need sufficient time to liftoff. But, even if you are free of time-related anxieties and know how to fly a plane, ‘Tutorialitis’ makes us forget that there are many different kinds of planes! My mistake until recently was not calibrating for the various shapes of learning curves when picking up new skills. I subconsciously subscribed to the binary of a flat and steep learning curve. Not every plane is nimble though. Keeping that in mind is probably a good idea.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><br/></p> <p><br/></p> <p><br/></p> <p><br/></p>]]></content><author><name>Jaidev Shriram</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on overcoming learning anxiety and managing expectations]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Treading the Waters of the Diversity Pool</title><link href="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2020/div-pool/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Treading the Waters of the Diversity Pool"/><published>2020-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2020/div-pool</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2020/div-pool/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Originally published in <a href="https://pingiiit.org/2020/08/diversity-pool/">Ping! - student magazine at IIIT-H</a>.</em></p> <p>It is winter 2020 and for the first time in recent history, there are more than 75 girls in the freshers batch at IIIT. Discussions ensue over whether their place in the institute is well-deserved. Strike that. The discussions have already begun. The introduction of the diversity pool has been one of the most polarizing decisions in recent times. As questions of female entitlement and ‘undeserved’ assistance pervade our mail chains and forum posts, a conversation about the inception of the Diversity Pool becomes a necessity. Through this article, we wish to shed some light on the fires that the Diversity Pool will put out - the invisible forces that often restrict women from succeeding in the tech world, whilst also exploring the social stigmas and restrictions that inhibit them from joining it. Many circumstances referenced in this article may not immediately be relatable to some, but that does not make them any less true. The inability to relate to an experience or incident does not invalidate an argument but rather exposes our lack of awareness of the issue. These experiences may be attributed to being a woman in technology, a student in India, and most importantly, a student at IIIT. Hence, we have to find out for ourselves and work against the structures that systematically limit minorities.</p> <h2 id="societal-reform">Societal Reform</h2> <p>When looking at schemes such as the Diversity pool, it is critical to note the society that necessitates it. It was created as a consequence of societal disparities in India and the broader tech world.</p> <h3 id="the-indian-context">The Indian Context</h3> <h4 id="access-to-coaching-centres">Access to coaching centres</h4> <p>India is a nation notorious for its mistreatment of women where gruesome incidents against them are commonplace. The instinctive response for most parents in the face of such incidents is to “protect” their children by limiting their interactions and freedom, favouring education that is closer-to-home. This inadvertently affects a girl’s access to education, risking losing out on greater learning opportunities in favour of “safer” options.</p> <p>A survey of female students at IIIT that wrote the JEE suggested this. Thirty-five female undergraduates who wrote the JEE were surveyed and asked a variety of questions on the coaching centres they attended. Normally this would’ve been a small sample size, but only ~52 girls have entered via the JEE mode in the past four years! Students were asked if they had ever attended a residential coaching institute, the likes of which are popular in Kota and are a common point of origin for many male IIIT students. A mere 4 girls across all the UG batches had attended a residential coaching institute. This is definitely far fewer than the percentage of male students that avail education at Kota. Some reasons they cited were their parents’ scepticism for residential institutes and preference for nearby coaching facilities as they did not want their daughters travelling too far. The underlying point here is that when comparing two demographics and their performance on a common exam, we should also compare the equality in access to preparatory material. Girls are not on an equal footing at this front. The Diversity Pool helps alleviate the problem by providing high-quality education to otherwise capable girls that had to settle for less. Arguments that claim women should be treated no differently often ignore the premise that they did not have the same facilities in the first place.</p> <p>As part of the survey, several students also noted the difficulties of being in a male-dominated classroom. The responses ranged from casual sexism and neglect on the teacher’s behalf to a lack of female community. One such response stated that their professor once said: “it doesn’t matter if girls do bad anyway they’ll end up as wives but boys have no choice that’s why they have to do better”. Another noted a contrast in the learning process where boys could stay at the institute for longer hours and clear their doubts while they couldn’t. Some girls even remarked that they “hated” their coaching institutes due to the awkwardness in interactions and partiality shown by teachers. The dismal number of girls in a class was a common feeling amongst most answers.</p> <p>Whilst some students did not note any difficulties, the mere existence of the aforementioned issues is a concerning factor. After all, if women are unable to find a conducive learning environment, we cannot expect them to outshine the men who had a better experience.</p> <h4 id="stigma-against-women-joining-tech">Stigma Against Women Joining Tech</h4> <p>Whilst we have progressed in our thinking, the idea of a female engineer is still foreign in many households. Considered to be “caring” individuals, women outnumber men in sciences such as medicine but still have abysmal numbers in engineering. Even if women didn’t have the barrier to a great education, the social stigma against female engineers is enough to suppress the number of women entering the field. In fact, just under a third of all JEE aspirants were girls in Jan 2020<d-footnote>https://www.shiksha.com/engineering/articles/number-of-jee-main-registrations-2020-decline-ews-and-women-applicants-on-the-rise-blogId-24783</d-footnote> and the numbers are often worse in JEE coaching centres (several students noted being just one of 3-4 girls in a class of 50 in the earlier survey). This stigma even limits the amount of expenditure on a girl child’s education in some households.</p> <p>Mindsets cannot be changed instantaneously but increased representation helps aid the process. As the number of women in technology matches those of men, the idea of a woman in tech will become the norm rather than the exception. Measures such as the Diversity Pool help increase these numbers gradually. As more women gain access to better learning opportunities, we break the myth of computer science being a masculine profession. The hope is that a balanced gender ratio is maintained organically in the future, but when the current reality is not as rosy, we need to give a little push.</p> <p>Following the pool’s announcement, many wondered why “grassroot” methods weren’t employed in place of the pool. To the institute’s credit, several efforts are being made to affect change at the lowest level. Admission modes such as SPEC specifically target girls from poorer economic backgrounds (along with integrated program students). Admission fee waivers and relaxed tuition further incentivize reluctant families to fund the girl child’s education. As with all benefit programmes, potential misuse is possible but hopefully, the larger result is constructive.</p> <h3 id="women-in-tech">Women in Tech</h3> <p>Poor access to education is just one facet of the problem though. Globally, women form a minority in the tech industry, and the numbers in India are no better. Just around 34% of the workforce is female as per <d-footnote>https://www.livemint.com/companies/news/in-india-34-women-are-in-tech-jobs-but-we-at-anitab-org-want-to-take-this-to-50-1569410199742.html</d-footnote><d-footnote>https://anitab.org/blog/indian-women-in-technology-barriers/</d-footnote>, a global non-profit social enterprise. The number of women in executive positions is much worse - just 1%. These numbers may be a consequence of the low number of women pursuing CS streams, but there’s more to the story.</p> <p>Women in tech frequently report mistreatment at their jobs, or dismissals because of their gender. Things only get worse when maternity matters come into play. The New York Times has an analytical piece on some “almost CEOs” that were stopped in their ascent to the top. A lack of camaraderie and general hostility towards assertive women seem to be the common thread even in multinational companies. This atmosphere wasn’t discovered recently though, it’s crept into our psyche and exists across domains. In tech, it is particularly ugly. One just needs to look at the comment sections on pages, or viral gaffes from male executives to see a lack of appreciation for women in tech. Unfortunately, it’s hard to visualize or fully grasp the scale of corporate misogyny but the word of thousands of women should be convincing enough. There is a problem, and it isn’t going to be solved overnight.</p> <p>Why is the world of corporations relevant at the university level though? It’s relevant because university is the route to such positions, to begin with! A shortage of women in tech shouldn’t be surprising if it’s known that women barely pursue computer science. Boosting these numbers would diversify a masculine workforce and potentially help change the stereotypes that suppress success. Age-old beliefs that are fueled by a lack of women in tech can only be broken over time with increased visibility. Soon, greater representation at higher strata would automatically inspire young girls to pursue Computer Science as they have role models to look up to. When dealing with inherent sexism and mass disparities, the only way to change the system is to “break the wheel”.</p> <p>The advantage of a diverse workforce is not just social - a company can benefit from the different points of view and approaches that come from different life experiences. It can lead to more creativity and innovation that comes with a wider team perspective. Researchers have also shown having women on a team can improve team processes and boost group <d-footnote>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228196582_The_Role_of_Gender_in_Team_Collaboration_and_Performance</d-footnote>. Lastly, customers come from all walks of life.The more the make-up of your organization reflects your customers the more likely it is you’ll communicate effectively with them. You cannot expect a product to cater to everyone if only a section of people are designing it. Despite these tangible benefits, misogyny is rampant, indicating a deeper illogical divide in treatment of the sexes.</p> <h2 id="there-has-to-be-another-way">There has to be another way?</h2> <p>We may have convinced you that there is a need to improve the gender ratio in college. The question arises how do we improve representation? Is the diversity channel really the best way?</p> <p>The harsh reality of the situation is, families from poorer socio-economic backgrounds are likely disproportionately unwilling to educate the girl child. A combination of low income and an outdated mindset can limit a girl’s chances at quality high school education as well. The Diversity Pool admittedly, may not solve that immediately (It focuses on societal change largely that may change broader views in the future). IIIT could do more to help the situation, by promoting girl child education in schools, enabling them to be competitive in entrance examinations. Another solution to this would be imposing a new cutoff for lower income-brackets. This comes with concerns about academic rigour and feasibility. To be fair, the Diversity Pool has barely kicked into effect, and the results are yet to be seen. In a year, armed with data, IIIT will hopefully amend the process to further accommodate the most disadvantaged.</p> <p>On matters of implementation, a commonly suggested solution is conducting a different exam for girls - along the lines of SPEC. A different mode of admission would not be different in any way though. It too will always feel like a form of reservation. Imagine that the Diversity Pool was a new mode of admission called FASA. Under FASA, these students would write an exam and compete for a limited number of seats - just like DASA. But here, FASA admits and regular JEE admits would belong to the same socio-economic groups. The difference lies only in the gender and the perception that no seats are being taken from boys in JEE. Couldn’t some FASA seats be given to the JEE mode? This argument can largely hold for most modes of admissions as well. The Diversity Pool isn’t any different from any modes of admission in that sense. No seats are being taken away from the boys; there’s a separate 25% “quota” for girls. The Diversity Pool will use JEE, lending the perception of standard reservation. The choice of using JEE is also for the greater good. As the speaker of parliament said, “The JEE reaches out to 11 Lakh students. Implementing another exam would, in fact, just bring down student quality. This itself is one of the ‘problems’ highlighted by those who oppose the Diversity pool.”</p> <p>Things aren’t perfect. It’s hard to imagine a perfect system that considers equity in access, income, societal pressures, and more to handpick students. For all the flaws that could be pointed out, the Diversity Pool pushes for a greater female community in tech. That’s a good start.</p> <h2 id="how-the-diversity-pool-will-change-iiit">How the Diversity Pool Will Change IIIT</h2> <p>The diversity channel may have been created to reshape societal structures that discourage women from joining technology but it also stands to reshape dynamics within IIIT. Contrary to popular belief, these reforms are unlikely to dilute the quality of students at IIIT but rather, create a positive and holistic learning environment, whilst sensitizing students about other genders.</p> <p>A common misconception amongst people is that your JEE rank dictates your professional and personal capabilities for the rest of your life. To all those who have taken the test, we can agree that our performance depends a lot on calming our nerves on exam day and also involves a considerable amount of luck. While rank 3,000 and rank 10,000 sound like they are poles apart, they are different just in terms of a mere 4-5 questions.</p> <p>We have seen proof of this as students with worse JEE ranks perform just as well (and sometimes even better) than their counterparts. The reality is that there is no conclusive correlation between how a person performs in the JEE versus how they fare in college. The inclusion of more girls through a diversity pool does not compromise the credibility or merit of the institute. Rather, it makes us more inclusive and paves way for more female perspective in discussions and deliberations.</p> <h3 id="impact-on-internal-misogyny">Impact on Internal Misogyny</h3> <p>Our perception of gender discrimination is generally limited to what we read in the media - loud instances of sexual harassment and the pay gap at workplaces. However, chauvinism is not limited to the higher rungs of the industry as it takes its roots right at the college level, before ballooning into something far more toxic. IIIT itself is not a conducive environment for existing women as misogyny pervades every sphere of our campus life.</p> <p>Modern sexism is more subtle than labelling women as entirely incapable - at IIIT, it takes the form of attributing a woman’s successes to her peers. Women regularly face mental harassment as their work is belittled and they are labelled manipulative or even cunning for availing any gender-specific opportunity. A recent explosive discussion on IIIT’s Facebook group for students evolved into a conversation about lewd comments and humour revolving around these diversity programs. Whatever be your opinion of such schemes, we do believe there is a more fruitful way for the community to debate them, rather than demeaning and degrading an entire gender. The confessions page at IIIT is another instance of unchecked sexualization where unwarranted comments are regularly made about a woman’s appearance. More concerning than some of the comments itself is their repeated nature.</p> <p>Such phenomena breed because of the stark minority of women in the college; whenever anyone speaks up, they are ignored or dismissed. These experiences often leave women feeling uncomfortable and instils in them a fear of being excluded and/or alienated by their male peers. With the lack of representation, comes a lack of apprehension for such issues on campus. Hence, the first step towards building a better community involves diversifying it. Inducting more girls into college can help achieve this as it will dismantle the toxic environment against women and no longer allow for an entire gender to be overshadowed by the majority. As they say ‘strength lies in numbers’ and that cannot be achieved with the ratio at an exiguous 1:10 figure.</p> <h3 id="a-newfound-community">A Newfound Community</h3> <p>Critical to every university experience is the community that lets it thrive. The female community at IIIT is rather small and often misses out on diverse viewpoints that larger groups can offer. A significant part of our college life is the discussions and interactions in our hostel rooms but these are severely limited for the girls, owing to their low numbers. These include both informal interactions and intellectual discussions.</p> <p>There is a lack of precedence for women taking part in many activities such as competitive programming and open-source contributions. The sheer number of boys pursuing it and the absence of visible female role models can be intimidating and overwhelming. This phenomenon has become especially worse in the past few years as there used to be many women GSoC’ers and competitive programmers earlier. The declining participation is likely due to the dwindling gender ratio (IIIT-H actually maintained a healthy gender ratio till 4 years back - it has only worsened recently). Whilst often overlooked, the lack of such a female community is a crucial point of debate. Greater intake can help build a strong and empowered female clique at IIIT. Subsequently, the ‘Outsider Syndrome’ that plagues women in STEM may be eradicated as they feel a sense of belonging to the larger community, allowing for richer discourse.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>A shortsighted view of the topic may deem the channel unfair and unnecessary, but a deeper analysis highlights the years of discrimination against women in engineering - from the lack of role models, overprotective parents, preference for the education of a male counterpart to mental and physical harassment in work environments, and the outright rejection of the scientific aptitude amongst females.</p> <p>Including more women in the field not only tackles the societal problem of gender diversity in STEM but also improves the standard of innovation and invention as one cannot quantify the diversity of thought and approach of a female perspective. The best time to increase representation is at the university level when students gain mastery in their subjects.</p> <p>For an institute that prides itself in its inclusive and progressive nature, we must take proactive efforts to improve the status of women in our college. Whilst all the deep-rooted issues surrounding gender inequality in STEM cannot be changed overnight, the Diversity Pool is a step in the right direction. We cannot wait around for mindsets and perspectives regarding women to change organically and must take immediate and dynamic measures that destroy such sexist structures.</p> <p>The Diversity Pool is neither the definitive answer nor the damnable evil - it is just a step in the right direction. If executed well, a balanced gender ratio will be maintained naturally in the future, without the need for targeted schemes. Rather than nitpicking over fine details and finding faults with the institute, it is high time we rally behind the pool, help make IIIT an all-inclusive space, and break the glass ceiling around STEM. ■</p>]]></content><author><name>Jaidev Shriram</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A dive into the Diversity Pool at IIIT-H - why it's good.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What if …? Considerations For a IIIT Post Pandemic</title><link href="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2020/iiit-post-pandemic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if …? Considerations For a IIIT Post Pandemic"/><published>2020-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2020/iiit-post-pandemic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaidevshriram.com/blog/2020/iiit-post-pandemic/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Originally published in <a href="https://pingiiit.org/2020/08/diversity-pool/">Ping! - student magazine at IIIT-H</a>.</em></p> <p>Once the current situation boils over, there is likely going to be a push worldwide to restore the status quo. Nothing could be worse for the world than a rushed attempt to return to the past, without acknowledging the difficulties and hurdles that entire communities braved through to date. With the pandemic came a string of changes that were forced on all, a complete shift in our perception of how various activities could be carried out. We became tuned to the need for social interaction, realized what meetings truly could’ve just been messages, and above all broke the monotony of our regular life. The same monotony that has defined how we carry out the day to day has also suppressed critique over why our routines exist to begin with. The hidden silver lining, for those who intend to emerge from this, is that the COVID pandemic has offered several the room to analyze and rethink their activities. For us at IIIT, the pandemic turned our entire academic system upside down in nearly every sense. Examinations were cancelled for all, attendance was ignored, grading was relaxed extremely with even Pass/Fail as an option! A student in 2019 would have considered these to be unimaginable under standard circumstances. Here, we speculate about the future for IIIT post-pandemic, drawing from the lessons that this academic year has taught us.</p> <h2 id="what-if-we-could-p-everything-and-other-considerations">What if we could P* everything? And Other Considerations</h2> <h3 id="the-new-grading-scheme">The New Grading Scheme</h3> <p>The COVID situation required the institute to make a decision about the way the remainder of the semester was to be conducted, and they had to make the decision quickly. The students were pleasantly surprised to see that there was a change in the grading scheme. The new scheme basically entailed two major changes:</p> <ol> <li>The grades to be given were just A,B,C and W in some courses, which means the students could withdraw the grade instead of it showing an F.</li> <li>Students had the choice to P* certain courses, which meant that the course would not count towards GPA considering the extenuating circumstances.</li> </ol> <p>This change in grading scheme begs the question: Can this scheme be a viable alternative for future semesters? There are two considerations here – reducing the number of letter grades to just three (A, B, C) and giving students an option to mask their grade in any course.</p> <h3 id="the-abc-system">The ABC system</h3> <p>This is quite an interesting consideration simply because it is extremely advantageous to students. All minus grades will mostly get bumped up, boosting one’s GPA. Students would have likely been satisfied with such a system this semester considering the grades that they’ve gotten but this semester’s experiment is marred by the lax grading curve due to the pandemic. In a more general scenario, it is possible that the cutoffs for A be higher than the regular A- depending on the professor. But, even if this was a good solution for students, it is impractical for other reasons.</p> <p>Just three letter grades is barely a precise depiction of student calibre since an excellent performer and a good performer have virtually no differentiation. This difference is a generally good measure for external recruiters and professors to gauge a students performance. Hence, it’s unlikely that this system continues in the long run.</p> <h3 id="p-ing-courses">P* ing courses</h3> <p>It’s immediately apparent that giving students an option to P* any course could result in a very masked transcript. Additionally, the GPA would likely be inflated for most due to masking. It is the existence of GPA that fundamentally makes P*ing unlikely.</p> <p>At Brown University, students have the option to take a course with a Satisfactory/No Credit grading initially. Here, students are required to choose between a graded scheme and the ungraded version before course completion. The critical difference between IIIT and Brown is that Brown does not calculate GPA! Without a GPA, external recruiters are forced to look at transcripts or self-evaluations from students to gauge their performance. Hence, GPA inflation is hardly a concern. Interestingly, Brown also uses A, B, C grading permanently and does not mark Fail grades on transcripts. Another difference is that the students are required to make their decision within 4 weeks of the start of the course, and not after the grades are released.</p> <p>Perhaps IIIT can still adopt a P* option while maintaining a GPA regardless. The point of university is to expand one’s horizons and more often than not, it entails enrolling in a course out of pure curiosity. If students had the option to take a limited number of electives as P/F while enrolling in it, students could focus on experimentation rather than work on maximizing their CGPA.</p> <p>Some optimists might argue that it is in IIIT’s best interest to help students maximize their CGPA. After all, shouldn’t coming from a top tier institute be reflected in their grade? Unfortunately, if unlimited P*ing is an option, then the CGPA loses its meaning entirely. The institute has an obligation to report grades accurately such that student performance can be well understood by others. It is this trust and reputation of the university that helps build the esteem of the institute – not just the GPA of a student.</p> <h2 id="what-if-there-were-recorded-and-live-streamed-lectures">What if there were recorded and live-streamed lectures?</h2> <h3 id="why-it-makes-sense">Why it makes sense</h3> <p>Given the existing infrastructure for recording lectures (cameras, audio feed,etc) in some classrooms, it makes sense to implement a system of recording/live streaming lectures since it would not require a lot of additional setup. The little amount of extra work actually required is greatly outweighed by the advantages, as we will see. It also opens up many avenues for students in a helpless situation, which would otherwise have an adverse impact on their performance.</p> <h3 id="recorded-lectures">Recorded lectures</h3> <h4 id="the-good">The good</h4> <p>Most students are aware that there is often a mutual exclusion between academics, specifically attending classes, and extracurricular activities. Students who find an opportunity to represent the college in any sort of competition usually find that it happens exactly when they have a lecture. There is also the issue that even if a student is willing to lose attendance for a lecture, it is not easy to make up the material covered in class that day.</p> <p>Not having to sacrifice participation would go a long way for the students, and improve IIIT’s reputation of not having extracurriculars.</p> <p>Even if a student is able to attend the lecture, it is still entirely possible that they can’t make the most of it (especially the lectures the day after a deadline). By having recorded lectures that students can access at any time, they can rewatch whatever parts they feel need a revisit.</p> <p>Though it can be argued that there are office hours for TAs and professors for just this purpose, it isn’t easy to ask someone to repeat a concept multiple times without feeling like their time is being wasted, especially if that someone is a professor or TA. Recorded lectures solve this by enabling the student to pause, rewind the lecture whenever they need, as many times as they want.</p> <h4 id="the-bad-and-sadly-the-ugly">The bad, and sadly, the ugly</h4> <p>Having recorded lectures sure paints a rosy picture, and it may seem like there could be no possible drawbacks of having such a system. Sadly, like most things in life, there’s a bad side to it as well.</p> <p>There now need to be people responsible for getting the professor’s direct audio feed, focussing the camera on the board when required and editing the videos, to name a few.</p> <p>There’s also the fact that the administration will need to upload the lectures regularly, and professors also need to ensure that the material is correctly uploaded. This extra effort on an already overworked staff may not be worth it.</p> <h3 id="live-streamed-lectures">Live Streamed lectures</h3> <h4 id="benefits">Benefits</h4> <p>One of the worst feelings students experience is having to attend classes when one isn’t feeling well. Since it isn’t easy to cover the missed material, most students force themselves to attend class. This not only causes overexertion to the unwell student but puts other students at risk as well. As we all know very well, it is very easy to spread infection. If the student was able to live stream the class, they would not have to miss the content covered that day.</p> <p>In 1918, when it was announced that the restrictions imposed to combat the Spanish Flu were removed, people poured onto the streets, cheering. As we know, 1918 was far from the last of the flu. Since humans (hopefully) learn from history, it is pretty much guaranteed that social distancing will be enforced for months to come after the pandemic is under control. Live streaming is a great solution to avoid having to put the brakes on classes and academics.</p> <h4 id="drawbacks">Drawbacks</h4> <p>It is very likely that students would misuse the freedom given to them, and just live stream classes from their rooms. Though limitations on the number of live streams allowed for a student can be imposed, it is still very easy to get distracted when not in class (in class too :p). This could be limited with an upper cap on the number of live streams permitted – though that would be a complex system to administer</p> <p>There is the added concern of doubts piling up. If students have doubts after watching the live stream, they can only clear them in the professor’s/TA’s office hours. Hence, it is very likely that many students would need their doubts to be cleared in the same slot, especially nearing exams.</p> <h3 id="the-professors-perspective-matters-too">The professor’s perspective matters too!</h3> <p>Professors will have their fair share of concerns with recorded/live-streamed lectures. For starters, it’s quite possible that students will pay less attention to the lectures. Some professors were also not very keen on having their lectures recorded even during the lockdown since they believe that students would just watch the lectures later, most probably nearing an assignment or quiz.</p> <h2 id="what-if-there-was-no-attendance">What if there was no attendance?</h2> <p>The ratings of the movie ‘Cats’, Joe Biden’s approval ratings, and the attendance in IIIT’s courses. Each witnessed a significant drop this year and defied all expectations and predictions of what it could be. As a consequence of the pandemic, IIIT adopted a zero mandatory attendance policy nearly a week before suspending on-campus teaching. It’s what most students wish for regularly but here, the situation demanded it.</p> <p>The past two months have been an interesting experiment of a zero attendance policy without a doubt. While the circumstances may be dire, and access to high internet speed questionable for many, conclusions about the practicality of the system can still be made. Across courses, professors expressed concern about attendance that wasn’t in line with the number of those who raised concerns. This is precisely why this can be viewed as an experiment for zero attendance – there were enough people with access to courseware reducing bias errors.</p> <h3 id="the-numbers">The Numbers</h3> <p>There is no discernable trend for attendance across the online-half of the semester. While attendance was remarkably high in the initial week, before the no attendance policy was confirmed, the subsequent weeks witnessed a sharp drop which then stagnated. In some courses, the final classes witnessed just under 10 attendees, while others had nearly 70% attendance. Hence, when given the opportunity to not attend any class at all, even the same students acted differently depending on the course. These numbers are, however, influenced by the existence of lecture recordings. Hence, there are two considerations to be kept in mind.</p> <h3 id="a-system-with-recordings">A System with Recordings</h3> <p>With recordings available, many students skipped classes, choosing to watch the lectures when the relevant assignment or activity came up. Some even chose to “binge” lectures at a time, at a higher speed which many personally prefer. Generally, it let students follow a different timetable altogether without compromising on the quality of instruction. The merits of such deviant activities is a different discussion altogether but on the matter of practicality, a zero attendance policy with recorded lecture seems difficult.</p> <p>It is very likely that the same poor turnout is repeated in subsequent iterations as the environment would likely be similar. But, the merits of having recorded lectures needn’t counter the merits of a lax attendance policy. The mere possibility of in-class quizzes will obviously bring a quick change, as any BITS student would testify. Other in-class activities, even non-graded ones could potentially counter the drop in numbers, emphasizing the need for interactive classrooms. Alternative attendance methods could be considered as well. Here, professors could have the discretion to set their own attendance requirement. This is practical for math-heavy courses for instance, where missing a few lectures leaves students no option but to miss more since topics just pile up. Hence, setting a higher requirement could curb significant drops in attendance.</p> <h3 id="a-system-without-recordings">A System Without Recordings</h3> <p>Unfortunately, there are few data points to estimate student interaction in a regular scenario with zero attendance. The two-weeks prior to the suspension of on-campus teaching is a poor datapoint because of social distancing requirements. Even if intentions to socially distance are ignored, this is biased because of the knee jerk reaction to the newfound freedom. An accurate test of student behaviour with such a system would require a much longer testing period. Regardless, the pandemic has taught us the importance of isolating oneself when ill, to prevent infecting others. At IIIT, the sheer pressure of not being able to miss more than four classes leads ill individuals to attend class, potentially infecting their classmates. A relaxation in the attendance policy is undoubtedly necessary to accommodate for this.</p> <h2 id="what-if-iiit-had-opencourseware">What if IIIT had OpenCourseWare?</h2> <p>Most, if not all college students are familiar with MIT’s OpenCourseWare website, which provides access to learning material for hundreds of courses, by some of the best professors in the world. Not only is there reading material, but the lectures are also recorded and uploaded as well. It’s almost like we’re sitting in MIT. There’s a similar Government initiative in India called NPTEL. IITs from all over the country add material on the website and pool resources. Having such a system, however, comes with its pros and cons.</p> <h3 id="pros">Pros</h3> <p>The most obvious advantage is that thousands of students now get access to some of the best teaching and resources at the click of a button. Especially in countries like India, where not all have the luxury of attending college, let alone good ones, it would be a huge help for such people.</p> <p>There is also the benefit that IIIT’s reputation improves. Since it is a tier-1 institute, by providing access to high-quality material and resources for thousands of students, it only improves its image. For instance, if there was an OpenCourseWare system set up before the lockdown, students who are interested in doing a course at this time would find IIIT to be a godsend.</p> <p>Many would say having just assignments and video lectures don’t simulate being in IIIT. Many other factors such as student competition, research, course structure, TAs etc play a major role in making an IIIT course what it is. While this is true, the assignments are still a great way to learn, and since the course structure is still maintained in OpenCourseWare, it goes a long way to help those who need it.</p> <h3 id="cons">Cons</h3> <p>The same problems faced in implementing a recorded lecture system are also faced here. Supposing there is a system for recorded lectures already in place, there is still the concern of maintaining the site and ensuring that the required material is uploaded.</p> <h3 id="copyright-and-accessibility">Copyright and accessibility</h3> <p>Having online content is a two-sided coin. On one hand, the laws on educational institutions using material are pretty favourable towards the institutes. In one case, a certain publisher filed a case against DU for infringing upon their copyright by photocopying the material and offering it as a part of a coursepack<d-footnote>https://blog.ipleaders.in/copyrighted-materials/ </d-footnote>. However, the High Court ruled against the publisher, saying that it is within the rights of an educational institution to use the material as required.</p> <p>Like India in Australia, UK and US Copyright laws specifically state that fair use of a copyrighted work or materials by educational institutions is not an infringement. Fair use involves the reproduction of copyrighted materials and any other uses that would be considered as an infringement. In India, copyright laws related to the usage of copyrighted materials in the educational institutions are very clear and strong. The fair dealing of copyrighted materials for educational institutions is limited to the extent it is used “in the course of instructions”.</p> <p>On the other hand, there are many restrictions on having online content.</p> <p>For example, the University of California, Berkeley was made to remove thousands of online lectures in response to a U.S Justice Department order<d-footnote>https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2017/03/06/u-california-berkeley-delete-publicly-available-educational-content</d-footnote>. The university had violated the Americans with Disabilities Act, since their videos lacked subtitles, screen reader compatibility and other issues.</p> <p>In India, Section 42 of the Act requires that the Government take measures to ensure that :</p> <p>“(i) all contents available in audio, print and electronic media are in accessible format; (ii) persons with disabilities have access to electronic media by providing audio description, sign language interpretation and close captioning; (iii) electronic goods and equipment which are meant for everyday use are available in universal design.”</p> <p>There are many such conditions to be met, and missing even one could result in all the content to be taken down. It is thus important to ensure that all these conditions are met, or it would all be for nought.</p> <p>It’s important to mention that implementing OpenCourseWare is looking far ahead into the future, and is a secondary concern to recorded and live-streamed lectures since it is only possible to implement when we have the infrastructure for recording lectures anyway.</p> <h2 id="what-if-there-was-another-crisis">What if there was another crisis?</h2> <p>Much can be said of IIIT’s response to the COVID pandemic – it was a nearly flawless response that stands out as one of the few great pandemic responses by colleges in India. While the decisions made for safety, hygiene, and academics, etc might have been received very well – they are all reactionary measures. That isn’t necessarily bad but there is always more that can be done. The question here is – is IIIT ready for another crisis situation?</p> <p>Disasters could range from electrical fires to the less likely natural disaster, each with ravaging consequences for IIIT. An incident such as a fire in a hostel cannot be solved with reactionary measures. Such rapid disasters require extensive preparedness and a community that is trained to respond to such situations. After all, there are just a few minutes during a fire incident to evacuate an entire building</p> <p>As part of the human values shivir for the batch of 2018, UG2 students were taught evacuation procedures along with general safety measures for a disaster. The effectiveness of the drills, however, is questionable based on student participation. Regardless, this is just one of four undergraduate batches that have been trained in safety procedure. When 2/3rd of Bakul Nivas residents aren’t trained, existing efforts are nearly meaningless. It is critical that IIIT conduct more mandatory awareness sessions for all those as they enter IIIT, along with occasional drills. Conducting these sessions at the start of the year is critical, as opposed to conducting it during one’s second year.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Hopefully, this summer won’t be an entirely cruel one, and the pandemic meets a quick end. Looking forward, it’s likely that even our monsoon becomes an online semester based on current trends. The sad reality is that the future is unbelievably unpredictable. That being said, there’s always a silver lining. The pandemic situation helped us look into possible alternatives to grading and online lectures, which was previously thought to be a distant dream. Though it is hard to tell if and when any of these may actually be implemented, the points mentioned in the article do make a note of the many considerations to be made for such a system. By taking the required precautions, we may be able to return to our regular lives soon</p>]]></content><author><name>Jaidev Shriram</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The pandemic changed things for better or worse. What lessons can we learn?]]></summary></entry></feed>